Identification Information: 
  Citation: 
    Citation Information: 
      Originator: Alberta Energy and Utilities Board
      Originator: Alberta Geological Survey
      Originator: Pana, D.I.
      Originator: Waters, E.J.
      Publication Date: 2015
      Title: GIS compilation of structural elements in Alberta, version 3.0 (GIS data, line features)
      Edition: v. 3.0
      Geospatial Data Presentation Form: vector digital data
      Series Information: 
        Series Name: Digital Data
        Issue Identification: DIG 2003-0012
      Publication Information: 
        Publication Place: Edmonton, Alberta, Canada
        Publisher: Alberta Energy Regulator
      Online Linkage: http://ags.aer.ca/document/DIG/DIG_2003_0012.zip
  Description: 
    Abstract: This dataset (lineaments_ln_ll.shp) comprises structural features compiled into GIS format from existing literature, published up to 2003. The data represent fault/lineament locations known or inferred in the Alberta Plains. We have chosen to digitize and publish all lineaments from source maps even where they extended beyond the Alberta boundary.  Each compiled feature is characterized by a set of attributes including: affected formations (oldest affected and oldest non-affected stratigraphic unit), fault type, fault sense of displacement, evidence used to infer the fault/lineament, original reference information and publication scale, and an estimate of the georeferencing error. The completeness of the captured attribute set varies for each feature as a function of the level of detail in the source article.  The data set should be used cautiously. First, the original authors’ interpretation of subsurface faults, particularly of ‘basement faults’, from air photo or satellite imagery lineaments is tenuous. Second, the vast majority of faults inferred in the foreland basin (Alberta Plains) east of the deformation front are normal-slip faults; although only the dip slip component has been inferred, some of these faults may also have a strike-slip component, generally not accounted for. Third, the location of lineaments includes cumulative errors inherent in the process of transferring into GIS lineaments traced by hand in the pre-computer era on small scale (regional) paper-copy maps. Such errors include spatial imprecisions in original lineament identification and drawing and errors in georefencing of the source map, as well as minor errors introduced during lineament digitization. Although each of them is minor at the scale of the original map, the cumulative effect of these errors may be significant and even misleading for large-scale (township or larger) projects.
    Purpose: The purpose of this dataset is not to show definitively where faults are located in Alberta. Rather it is to show, in a common geospatial environment, locations where structural elements have been identified in the scientific literature and what the evidence is for their postulation. We strongly advise users of this dataset to consult the original literature source associated with each feature of interest and draw their own conclusions as to the presence or absence of faulting at that location.
    Supplemental Information: Details of the compilation method and geological interpretation are published in English in: Pana, D., Waters, E.J. and Grobe, M. (2001): GIS compilation of structural elements in northern Alberta, release 1.0; Alberta Energy and Utilities Board, EUB/AGS Earth Sciences Report 2001-01
  Time Period of Content: 
    Time Period Information: 
      Single Date/Time: 
        Calendar Date: 2003
    Currentness Reference: publication date
  Status: 
    Progress: Complete
    Maintenance and Update Frequency: Irregular
  Spatial Domain: 
    Bounding Coordinates: 
      West Bounding Coordinate: -124.92196
      East Bounding Coordinate: -100.245045
      North Bounding Coordinate: 64.013218
      South Bounding Coordinate: 48.00311
  Keywords: 
    Theme: 
      Theme Keyword Thesaurus: none
      Theme Keyword: fault
      Theme Keyword: gis data
      Theme Keyword: lineaments
      Theme Keyword: peace river arch
      Theme Keyword: structural geology
      Theme Keyword: structure
    Place: 
      Place Keyword Thesaurus: None.
      Place Keyword: 72e
      Place Keyword: 72l
      Place Keyword: 72m
      Place Keyword: 73d
      Place Keyword: 73e
      Place Keyword: 73l
      Place Keyword: 73m
      Place Keyword: 74d
      Place Keyword: 74e
      Place Keyword: 74l
      Place Keyword: 74m
      Place Keyword: 82g
      Place Keyword: 82h
      Place Keyword: 82i
      Place Keyword: 82j
      Place Keyword: 82n
      Place Keyword: 82o
      Place Keyword: 82p
      Place Keyword: 83a
      Place Keyword: 83b
      Place Keyword: 83c
      Place Keyword: 83d
      Place Keyword: 83e
      Place Keyword: 83f
      Place Keyword: 83g
      Place Keyword: 83h
      Place Keyword: 83i
      Place Keyword: 83j
      Place Keyword: 83k
      Place Keyword: 83l
      Place Keyword: 83m
      Place Keyword: 83n
      Place Keyword: 83o
      Place Keyword: 83p
      Place Keyword: 84a
      Place Keyword: 84b
      Place Keyword: 84c
      Place Keyword: 84d
      Place Keyword: 84e
      Place Keyword: 84f
      Place Keyword: 84g
      Place Keyword: 84h
      Place Keyword: 84i
      Place Keyword: 84j
      Place Keyword: 84k
      Place Keyword: 84l
      Place Keyword: 84m
      Place Keyword: 84n
      Place Keyword: 84o
      Place Keyword: 84p
      Place Keyword: alberta
      Place Keyword: canada
  Access Constraints: Public
  Use Constraints: Acknowledgement of the Alberta Energy Regulator/Alberta Geological Survey as the originator/source of this information is required as described in the Open Government License - Alberta.
  Point of Contact: 
    Contact Information: 
      Contact Organization Primary: 
        Contact Organization: Alberta Geological Survey
        Contact Person: AGS Information Manager
      Contact Position: AGS Information Manager
      Contact Address: 
        Address Type: mailing and physical
        Address: Alberta Energy Regulator
        Address: 4th Floor, Twin Atria Building
        Address: 4999-98 Avenue NW
        City: Edmonton
        State or Province: Alberta
        Postal Code: T6B 2X3
        Country: Canada
      Contact Voice Telephone: (780) 638-4491
      Contact Facsimile Telephone: (780) 422-1918
      Contact Electronic Mail Address: AGS-Info@aer.ca
      Hours of Service: 8:00 a.m. to 12:00 p.m. and 1:00 p.m. to 4:30 p.m.
  Data Set Credit: E.J.Waters. C. Kehoe assisted with digitizing v. 3.
  Native Data Set Environment: Microsoft Windows 7 Enterprise Service Pack 1
  Cross Reference: 
    Citation Information: 
      Originator: Alberta Energy and Utilities Board
      Originator: Alberta Geological Survey
      Originator: Pana, D.I.
      Originator: Waters, E.J.
      Originator: Grobe, M.
      Publication Date: 2001
      Title: GIS Compilation of Structural Elements in Northern Alberta, Release 1.0
      Geospatial Data Presentation Form: document
      Series Information: 
        Series Name: Earth Sciences Report
        Issue Identification: ESR 2001-01
      Publication Information: 
        Publication Place: Edmonton, Alberta, Canada
        Publisher: Alberta Energy and Utilities Board
      Online Linkage: http://www.ags.gov.ab.ca/publications
Data Quality Information: 
  Logical Consistency Report: As this data set is a compilation there is no topological relationship implied in the linework for vectors from different published sources.  Thus, logical inconsistencies may arise where the same feature (such as the Great Slave Lake shear zone) is compiled from two or more literature sources.  Positional differences for a given fault may occur due to differences in input data accuracies.
  Completeness Report: This compilation records major lineaments in  Alberta, as published in the literature. A literature search identified other pertinent data from sources including assessment reports and press releases by mineral  exploration companies.
  Positional Accuracy: 
    Horizontal Positional Accuracy: 
      Horizontal Positional Accuracy Report: No formal accuracy check completed; digital accuracy estimated at better than +/- 5 km.  Each feature is coded with an estimate of its georeferencing accuracy.
  Lineage: 
    Source Information: 
      Source Citation: 
        Citation Information: 
          Originator: Alberta Research Council
          Originator: Alberta Geological Survey
          Originator: Langenberg, C.W.
          Publication Date: 1983
          Title: Polyphase Deformation in the Canadian Shield of Northeastern Alberta
          Geospatial Data Presentation Form: document
          Series Information: 
            Series Name: Bulletin
            Issue Identification: BUL 045
          Publication Information: 
            Publication Place: Edmonton, Alberta, Canada
            Publisher: Alberta Research Council
      Source Scale Denominator: 0
      Type of Source Media: paper
      Source Time Period of Content: 
        Time Period Information: 
          Single Date/Time: 
            Calendar Date: 1983
        Source Currentness Reference: publication date
      Source Citation Abbreviation: Langenberg, 1983
      Source Contribution: Cited in Comments for comparison purposes
    Source Information: 
      Source Citation: 
        Citation Information: 
          Originator: Hoffman, P.F.
          Originator: Bell, I.R.
          Originator: Hildebrand, R.S.
          Originator: Thorstad, L.
          Publication Date: 1977
          Title: Geology of the Athapuscow aulacogen, east arm of Great Slave Lake, N.W.T.
          Geospatial Data Presentation Form: document          Publication Information: 
            Publication Place: Edmonton, Alberta, Canada
            Publisher: Alberta Geological Survey
          Other Citation Details: In: Report of activities, Part A: Geological Survey of Canada Paper 77-1 A, p. 117-129.
      Source Scale Denominator: 0
      Type of Source Media: paper
      Source Time Period of Content: 
        Time Period Information: 
          Single Date/Time: 
            Calendar Date: 1977
        Source Currentness Reference: publication date
      Source Citation Abbreviation: Hoffman et al., 1977
      Source Contribution: Cited in Comments for comparison purposes
    Source Information: 
      Source Citation: 
        Citation Information: 
          Originator: McDonough, M.R.
          Originator: McNicoll, V.J.
          Originator: Schetselaar, E.M.
          Originator: Grover, T.W.
          Publication Date: 2000
          Title: Geochronological and kinematic constraints on crustal shortening and escape in a two-sided oblique-slip collisional and magmatic orogen, Paleoproterozoic Taltson magmatic zone, northeastern Alberta.
          Geospatial Data Presentation Form: document          Publication Information: 
            Publication Place: Edmonton, Alberta, Canada
            Publisher: Alberta Geological Survey
          Other Citation Details: Canadian Journal of Earth Sciences 37/11, 1549-1573.
      Source Scale Denominator: 0
      Type of Source Media: paper
      Source Time Period of Content: 
        Time Period Information: 
          Single Date/Time: 
            Calendar Date: 2000
        Source Currentness Reference: publication date
      Source Citation Abbreviation: McDonough et al., 2000
      Source Contribution: Cited in Comments for comparison purposes
    Source Information: 
      Source Citation: 
        Citation Information: 
          Originator: Hoffman, P.F.
          Publication Date: 1987
          Title: Continental transform tectonics: Great Slave Lake Shear Zone (1.9 Ga), northwest Canada.
          Geospatial Data Presentation Form: document          Publication Information: 
            Publication Place: 
            Publisher: 
          Other Citation Details: Geology, v. 15, p. 785-788.
      Source Scale Denominator: 0
      Type of Source Media: paper
      Source Time Period of Content: 
        Time Period Information: 
          Single Date/Time: 
            Calendar Date: 1987
        Source Currentness Reference: publication date
      Source Citation Abbreviation: Hoffman, 1987
      Source Contribution: Cited in Comments for comparison purposes
    Source Information: 
      Source Citation: 
        Citation Information: 
          Originator: Chacko, T.
          Originator: King, R.
          Originator: Muehlenbachs, K.
          Originator: Burwash, R.A.
          Publication Date: 
          Title: The Kimiwan Isotopic Anomaly, a low O-18 zone in the Precambrian basement of Alberta: constraints on the timing of O-18 depletion from K-Ar and Rb-Sr data
          Geospatial Data Presentation Form: document          Publication Information: 
            Publication Place: 
            Publisher: 
          Other Citation Details: In: LITHOPROBE Alberta Basement Transects: Report of Transect Workshop, Calgary, April 10-11, 1995, (ed.) G.M. Ross, LITHOPROBE Secretariat, University of British Columbia, LITHOPROBE Report 47, p. 335-339.
      Source Scale Denominator: 0
      Type of Source Media: paper
      Source Time Period of Content: 
        Time Period Information: 
          Single Date/Time: 
            Calendar Date: 1995
        Source Currentness Reference: publication date
      Source Citation Abbreviation: Chacko et al., 1995
      Source Contribution: Cited in Comments for comparison purposes
    Source Information: 
      Source Citation: 
        Citation Information: 
          Originator: Thomas, M.D.
          Originator: Gibb, R.A.
          Originator: Quince, J.R.
          Publication Date: 1976
          Title: New evidence from offset aeromagnetic anomalies for transcurrent faulting associated with the Bathurst and McDonald faults, Northwest Territories
          Geospatial Data Presentation Form: document          Publication Information: 
            Publication Place: 
            Publisher: 
          Other Citation Details: Canadian Journal of Earth Sciences, v. 13, p. 1244-1250.
      Source Scale Denominator: 0
      Type of Source Media: paper
      Source Time Period of Content: 
        Time Period Information: 
          Single Date/Time: 
            Calendar Date: 1976
        Source Currentness Reference: publication date
      Source Citation Abbreviation: Thomas et al., 1976
      Source Contribution: Cited in Comments for comparison purposes
    Source Information: 
      Source Citation: 
        Citation Information: 
          Originator: Dix, G.R.
          Publication Date: 1990
          Title: Stages of platform development in the Upper Devonian (Frasnian) Leduc Formation, Peace River Arch, Alberta
          Geospatial Data Presentation Form:          Publication Information: 
            Publication Place: 
            Publisher: 
          Other Citation Details: In: Geology of the Peace River Arch; S.C. O'Connell and J.S. Bell (eds), Bulletin of Canadian Petroleum Geology, 38A, p. 66-92
      Source Scale Denominator: 0
      Type of Source Media: paper
      Source Time Period of Content: 
        Time Period Information: 
          Single Date/Time: 
            Calendar Date: 1990
        Source Currentness Reference: publication date
      Source Citation Abbreviation: Dix, 1990
      Source Contribution: Cited in Comments for comparison purposes
    Source Information: 
      Source Citation: 
        Citation Information: 
          Originator: Wright, G.N.
          Originator: McMechan, M.E.
          Originator: Potter, D.E.G.
          Publication Date: 1993
          Title: Structure and Architecture of the Western Canada Sedimentary Basin
          Geospatial Data Presentation Form: document          Publication Information: 
            Publication Place: 
            Publisher: 
          Other Citation Details: In: Geological Atlas of the Western Canada Sedimentary Basin.  G.D. Mossop and I. Shetsen (compilers), Calgary; C.S.P.G. & Alberta Research Council, A.G.S., Chapter 3, p. 25-40
          Online Linkage: Not available online.
      Source Scale Denominator: 0
      Type of Source Media: paper
      Source Time Period of Content: 
        Time Period Information: 
          Single Date/Time: 
            Calendar Date: 1993
        Source Currentness Reference: publication date
      Source Citation Abbreviation: Wright et al. 1993
      Source Contribution: Cited in Comments for comparison purposes
    Source Information: 
      Source Citation: 
        Citation Information: 
          Originator: Kiernan, J.P.
          Publication Date: 1996
          Title: Tectonic controls in sedimentation and erosion in the Upper Cretaceous lower Kaskapau Formation, Peace River region, Alberta
          Geospatial Data Presentation Form: document          Publication Information: 
            Publication Place: 
            Publisher: 
          Other Citation Details: B.Sc. thesis, University of Western Ontario, 97 p.
      Source Scale Denominator: 0
      Type of Source Media: paper
      Source Time Period of Content: 
        Time Period Information: 
          Single Date/Time: 
            Calendar Date: 1996
        Source Currentness Reference: publication date
      Source Citation Abbreviation: Kiernan, 1996
      Source Contribution: Cited in Comments for comparison purposes
    Source Information: 
      Source Citation: 
        Citation Information: 
          Originator: McDonough, M.R.
          Originator: Grover, T.W.
          Originator: McNicoll, V.J.
          Originator: Lindsay, D.D.
          Originator: Kelly, K.L.
          Originator: Guerstein, P.G.
          Publication Date: 1994
          Title: Revised Geology, Mercredi Lake, Alberta - NWT (NTS 74M/15)
          Geospatial Data Presentation Form: map          Publication Information: 
            Publication Place: 
            Publisher: Geological Survey of Canada
          Other Citation Details: Open File 2904, Scale 1:50000
      Source Scale Denominator: 0
      Type of Source Media: paper
      Source Time Period of Content: 
        Time Period Information: 
          Single Date/Time: 
            Calendar Date: 1994
        Source Currentness Reference: publication date
      Source Citation Abbreviation: McDonough et al., 1994b
      Source Contribution: Cited in Comments for comparison purposes
    Source Information: 
      Source Citation: 
        Citation Information: 
          Originator: McDonough, M.R.
          Originator: Grover, T.W.
          Originator: McNicoll, V.J.
          Originator: Lindsay, D.D.
          Originator: Kelly, K.L.
          Originator: Guerstein, P.G.
          Publication Date: 1994
          Title: Revised Geology, Andrew Lake, Alberta - Saskatchewan - NWT (NTS 74M/16)
          Geospatial Data Presentation Form: map          Publication Information: 
            Publication Place: 
            Publisher: Geological Survey of Canada
          Other Citation Details: Open File 2905, Scale 1:50000
      Source Scale Denominator: 0
      Type of Source Media: paper
      Source Time Period of Content: 
        Time Period Information: 
          Single Date/Time: 
            Calendar Date: 1994
        Source Currentness Reference: publication date
      Source Citation Abbreviation: McDonough et al., 1994c
      Source Contribution: Cited in Comments for comparison purposes
    Source Information: 
      Source Citation: 
        Citation Information: 
          Originator: McDonough, M.R.
          Originator: Grover, T.W.
          Originator: McNicoll, V.J.
          Originator: Cooley, M.A.
          Originator: Schetselaar, E.M.
          Originator: Robinson N.N.
          Publication Date: 1994
          Title: Geology, Cornwall Lake, Alberta (NTS 74M/10)
          Geospatial Data Presentation Form: map          Publication Information: 
            Publication Place: 
            Publisher: Geological Survey of Canada
          Other Citation Details: Open File 2896, Scale 1:50000
      Source Scale Denominator: 0
      Type of Source Media: paper
      Source Time Period of Content: 
        Time Period Information: 
          Single Date/Time: 
            Calendar Date: 1994
        Source Currentness Reference: publication date
      Source Citation Abbreviation: McDonough et al., 1994e
      Source Contribution: Cited in Comments for comparison purposes
    Source Information: 
      Source Citation: 
        Citation Information: 
          Originator: Hiebert, S.N.
          Originator: Spratt, D.A.
          Publication Date: 1995
          Title: Geometry of the thrust front near Pincher Creek, Alberta
          Geospatial Data Presentation Form:          Publication Information: 
            Publication Place: 
            Publisher: 
          Other Citation Details: Bulletin of Canadian Petroleum Geology, vol. 44, no. 2, p.195-201.
      Source Scale Denominator: 0
      Type of Source Media: paper
      Source Time Period of Content: 
        Time Period Information: 
          Single Date/Time: 
            Calendar Date: 1995
        Source Currentness Reference: publication date
      Source Citation Abbreviation: Hiebert and Spratt, 1996
      Source Contribution: Cited in Comments for comparison purposes
    Source Information: 
      Source Citation: 
        Citation Information: 
          Originator: Russell, L.S.
          Originator: Landes, R.W.
          Publication Date: 1940
          Title: Geology of the Southern Alberta Plains
          Geospatial Data Presentation Form: document          Publication Information: 
            Publication Place: 
            Publisher: Geological Survey of Canada
          Other Citation Details: Department of Mines and Resources, Mines and Geology Branch, Bureau of Geology and Topography, Memoir 221, p.1-128.
      Source Scale Denominator: 0
      Type of Source Media: paper
      Source Time Period of Content: 
        Time Period Information: 
          Single Date/Time: 
            Calendar Date: 1940
        Source Currentness Reference: publication date
      Source Citation Abbreviation: Russell and Landes, 1940
      Source Contribution: Cited in Comments for comparison purposes
    Source Information: 
      Source Citation: 
        Citation Information: 
          Originator: Kanasewich, E.R.
          Originator: Clowes, R.M.
          Originator: McCloughan, C.H.
          Publication Date: 1968
          Title: A buried Precambrian rift in western Canada
          Geospatial Data Presentation Form: document          Publication Information: 
            Publication Place: 
            Publisher: 
          Other Citation Details: Tectonophysics, 8: 513-527.
      Source Scale Denominator: 0
      Type of Source Media: paper
      Source Time Period of Content: 
        Time Period Information: 
          Single Date/Time: 
            Calendar Date: 1968
        Source Currentness Reference: publication date
      Source Citation Abbreviation: Kanasewich et al., 1968
      Source Contribution: Cited in Comments for comparison purposes
    Source Information: 
      Source Citation: 
        Citation Information: 
          Originator: Burwash, R.A.
          Originator: Muehlenbachs, K.
          Publication Date: 1997
          Title: Tectonic setting of Eastern Alberta Basement granites inferred from Pearce trace element discrimination diagrams
          Geospatial Data Presentation Form: document          Publication Information: 
            Publication Place: 
            Publisher: 
          Other Citation Details: Alberta Basement Transects. Compiled by G.M. Ross. Lithoprobe Report 59, pp. 35-49.
      Source Scale Denominator: 0
      Type of Source Media: paper
      Source Time Period of Content: 
        Time Period Information: 
          Single Date/Time: 
            Calendar Date: 1997
        Source Currentness Reference: publication date
      Source Citation Abbreviation: Burwash and Muehlenbachs, 1997
      Source Contribution: Cited in Comments for comparison purposes
    Source Information: 
      Source Citation: 
        Citation Information: 
          Originator: Magrath, C.B.
          Publication Date: 1960
          Title: Multiple signals cause seismic problems at Taber
          Geospatial Data Presentation Form: document          Publication Information: 
            Publication Place: 
            Publisher: 
          Other Citation Details: Oil Week. Nov 5, pp. 38-39.
      Source Scale Denominator: 0
      Type of Source Media: paper
      Source Time Period of Content: 
        Time Period Information: 
          Single Date/Time: 
            Calendar Date: 1960
        Source Currentness Reference: publication date
      Source Citation Abbreviation: Magrath (1960)
      Source Contribution: Cited in Comments for comparison purposes
    Source Information: 
      Source Citation: 
        Citation Information: 
          Originator: Burwash, R.A.
          Originator: Culbert, R.R.
          Publication Date: 1976
          Title: Multivariate geochemical and mineral patterns in the Precambrian basement of western Canada
          Geospatial Data Presentation Form: document          Publication Information: 
            Publication Place: 
            Publisher: 
          Other Citation Details: Canadian Journal of Earth Sciences, 13: p. 1-18.
      Source Scale Denominator: 0
      Type of Source Media: paper
      Source Time Period of Content: 
        Time Period Information: 
          Single Date/Time: 
            Calendar Date: 1976
        Source Currentness Reference: publication date
      Source Citation Abbreviation: Burwash and Culbert (1976)
      Source Contribution: Cited in Comments for comparison purposes
    Source Information: 
      Source Citation: 
        Citation Information: 
          Originator: Burwash, R.A.
          Originator: Chacko, T.
          Originator: Muehlenbachs, K.
          Publication Date: 1995
          Title: Tectonic interpretation of Kimiwan Anomaly, Northwestern Alberta
          Geospatial Data Presentation Form:          Publication Information: 
            Publication Place: 
            Publisher: 
          Other Citation Details: Alberta Basement Transects. Edited by G.M. Ross. Lithoprobe Report 47, pp. 340-355.
      Source Scale Denominator: 0
      Type of Source Media: paper
      Source Time Period of Content: 
        Time Period Information: 
          Single Date/Time: 
            Calendar Date: 1995
        Source Currentness Reference: publication date
      Source Citation Abbreviation: Burwash et al. (1995)
      Source Contribution: Cited in Comments for comparison purposes
    Process Step: 
      Process Description: Georeferencing of linear features in the compilation was done in one of three ways, depending on their origin. 1)  Lineaments from figures derived from the Geological Atlas of the Western Canada Sedimentary Basin are archived by AGS as digital polylines in ASCII format contain the coordinates (i.e., latitude and longitude) of each vertex along the feature polylines.  These were  reassembled into georeferenced, ArcInfo coverage format of known projection and datum, using the Arc TRANSFORM command.
        2)  Other Geological Atlas figures are archived by AGS as Windows metafiles (*.wmf) as digital graphic files (vector format) that contain registration (fiducial) marks such as latitude-longitude graticules, township grids, etc., but are not georeferenced (i.e., they were created in a graphics software package using page coordinates, not map coordinates). The map projection of each figure was determined by trial and error. Once the projection parameters were determined, the files were transformed from page coordinates to map coordinates (using the Arc TRANSFORM command), and then converted to one common projection (ten-degree Transverse Mercator projection).
        3)  Paper maps from journal articles (i.e., non-digital), containing small-scale or complex features, were scanned, digitized in a graphics package, and then processed the same way as figures of Type 2. Relatively simple, large-scale features were sketched in against, for example, a digital township grid where adequate georeferencing information was shown on the figure.  
        Attribute information for each line feature, including unique identifier, reference, author's criteria for inferring a fault's existence (primary and secondary), formation(s) affected, fault type, dip direction of fault plane (where applicable/known) and AGS comments, were compiled into a Microsoft Access database.  Information queried from the database was joined to the spatial features in ArcView and written out in ESRI shapefile format.
      Process Date: 2003
    Process Step: 
      Process Description: In order to expand the coverage of this dataset from northern Alberta to all of Alberta, we selected several more references for digitizing.  Lineaments from 20 sources were georeferenced and added to the compilation.
      Process Date: 2003
    Process Step: 
      Process Description: We made numerous corrections and refinements to the entire dataset, including:
1. Adding the source publication scale to the shapefile’s attribute table, as ‘PubScale’.
2. Renaming the field ‘Up_Down’ to ‘HW_VOffset’ (hanging wall vertical offset), and modifying its values for clarity.
3. Correcting sentences previously truncated at 255 characters (a limitation of the shapefile attribute table field length).
4. The Comments field contains citations to literature sources not directly used in this compilation (i.e., no line features were digitized from them). We added full references for these to the dataset’s metadata under Data Quality, Lineage. 
5. Deleting a set of unpublished features (Abercrombie, 1999).
6. Correcting spelling errors.
      Process Date: 2015
Spatial Data Organization Information: 
  Direct Spatial Reference Method: Vector
  Point and Vector Object Information: 
    SDTS Terms Description: 
      SDTS Point and Vector Object Type: String
      Point and Vector Object Count: 2275
Spatial Reference Information: 
  Horizontal Coordinate System Definition: 
    Geographic: 
      Geographic Coordinate Units: Decimal degrees
      Latitude Resolution: 0.000000
      Longitude Resolution: 0.000000
    Geodetic Model: 
      Horizontal Datum Name: North American Datum of 1983
      Ellipsoid Name: Geodetic Reference System 80
      Semi-Major Axis: 6378137.000000
      Denominator of Flattening Ratio: 298.257222
  Vertical Coordinate System Definition: 
    Altitude System Definition: 
      Altitude Encoding Method: Explicit elevation coordinate included with horizontal coordinates
Entity and Attribute Information: 
  Detailed Description: 
    Entity Type: 
      Entity Type Label: lineaments_ln_ll.dbf
      Entity Type Definition: Structural lineaments compiled from literature
      Entity Type Definition Source: Alberta Geological Survey
    Attribute: 
      Attribute Label: FID
      Attribute Definition: Internal feature number.
      Attribute Definition Source: ESRI
      Attribute Domain Values: 
        Unrepresentable Domain: Sequential unique whole numbers that are automatically generated.
    Attribute: 
      Attribute Label: Shape
      Attribute Definition: Feature geometry.
      Attribute Definition Source: ESRI
      Attribute Domain Values: 
        Unrepresentable Domain: Coordinates defining the features.
    Attribute: 
      Attribute Label: ID
      Attribute Definition: Internal number.
      Attribute Definition Source: Alberta Geological Survey
      Attribute Domain Values: 
        Unrepresentable Domain: Whole numbers that are automatically generated.
    Attribute: 
      Attribute Label: LineID
      Attribute Definition: Unique feature identifier.
      Attribute Definition Source: Alberta Geological Survey
      Attribute Domain Values: 
        Unrepresentable Domain: Whole numbers that are automatically generated.
    Attribute: 
      Attribute Label: FmCode
      Attribute Definition: Formation code (numeric, increasing with increasing age)
      Attribute Definition Source: Alberta Geological Survey
      Attribute Domain Values: 
        Codeset Domain: 
          Codeset Name: EUB Table of Alberta Formation Codes (unpublished)
          Codeset Source: Alberta Energy and Utilities Board
    Attribute: 
      Attribute Label: FmName
      Attribute Definition: Formation name
      Attribute Definition Source: Alberta Geological Survey
      Attribute Domain Values: 
        Codeset Domain: 
          Codeset Name: EUB Table of Alberta Formation Codes (unpublished)
          Codeset Source: Alberta Energy and Utilities Board
    Attribute: 
      Attribute Label: UpFmCode
      Attribute Definition: Formation code of the uppermost formation affected by a fault (numeric, increasing with increasing age)
      Attribute Definition Source: Alberta Geological Survey
      Attribute Domain Values: 
        Codeset Domain: 
          Codeset Name: EUB Table of Alberta Formation Codes (unpublished)
          Codeset Source: Alberta Energy and Utilities Board
    Attribute: 
      Attribute Label: UpFmName
      Attribute Definition: Uppermost formation name
      Attribute Definition Source: Alberta Geological Survey
      Attribute Domain Values: 
        Codeset Domain: 
          Codeset Name: EUB Table of Alberta Formation Codes (unpublished)
          Codeset Source: Alberta Energy and Utilities Board
    Attribute: 
      Attribute Label: FaultSense
      Attribute Definition: Type of fault, with the main component of displacement
      Attribute Definition Source: Alberta Geological Survey
      Attribute Domain Values: 
        Enumerated Domain: 
          Enumerated Domain Value: Normal
          Enumerated Domain Value Definition: Normal fault
          Enumerated Domain Value Definition Source: None
        Enumerated Domain: 
          Enumerated Domain Value: Normal/Strike-Slip
          Enumerated Domain Value Definition: Normal/Strike-Slip fault
          Enumerated Domain Value Definition Source: None
        Enumerated Domain: 
          Enumerated Domain Value: Dextral
          Enumerated Domain Value Definition: Dextral fault
          Enumerated Domain Value Definition Source: None
        Enumerated Domain: 
          Enumerated Domain Value: Sinistral
          Enumerated Domain Value Definition: Sinistral fault
          Enumerated Domain Value Definition Source: None
        Enumerated Domain: 
          Enumerated Domain Value: Thrust
          Enumerated Domain Value Definition: Thrust fault
          Enumerated Domain Value Definition Source: None
        Enumerated Domain: 
          Enumerated Domain Value: Thrust/Strike-Slip
          Enumerated Domain Value Definition: Thrust/Strike-Slip fault
          Enumerated Domain Value Definition Source: None
        Enumerated Domain: 
          Enumerated Domain Value: Unknown
          Enumerated Domain Value Definition: Fault sense unknown
          Enumerated Domain Value Definition Source: None
    Attribute: 
      Attribute Label: DipDir
      Attribute Definition: Dip direction of fault plane
      Attribute Definition Source: Alberta Geological Survey
      Attribute Domain Values: 
        Range Domain: 
          Range Domain Minimum: 0
          Range Domain Maximum: 360
    Attribute: 
      Attribute Label: HW_VOffset
      Attribute Definition: Hanging wall vertical offset.
      Attribute Definition Source: Alberta Geological Survey
      Attribute Domain Values: 
        Enumerated Domain: 
          Enumerated Domain Value: N up
          Enumerated Domain Value Definition: North block up
          Enumerated Domain Value Definition Source: Alberta Geological Survey
        Enumerated Domain: 
          Enumerated Domain Value: S up
          Enumerated Domain Value Definition: South block up
          Enumerated Domain Value Definition Source: Alberta Geological Survey
        Enumerated Domain: 
          Enumerated Domain Value: E up
          Enumerated Domain Value Definition: East block up
          Enumerated Domain Value Definition Source: Alberta Geological Survey
        Enumerated Domain: 
          Enumerated Domain Value: W up
          Enumerated Domain Value Definition: West block up
          Enumerated Domain Value Definition Source: Alberta Geological Survey
        Enumerated Domain: 
          Enumerated Domain Value: NW up
          Enumerated Domain Value Definition: Northwest block up
          Enumerated Domain Value Definition Source: Alberta Geological Survey
        Enumerated Domain: 
          Enumerated Domain Value: NE up
          Enumerated Domain Value Definition: Northeast block up
          Enumerated Domain Value Definition Source: Alberta Geological Survey
        Enumerated Domain: 
          Enumerated Domain Value: SE up
          Enumerated Domain Value Definition: Southeast block up
          Enumerated Domain Value Definition Source: Alberta Geological Survey
        Enumerated Domain: 
          Enumerated Domain Value: SW up
          Enumerated Domain Value Definition: Southwest block up
          Enumerated Domain Value Definition Source: Alberta Geological Survey
        Enumerated Domain: 
          Enumerated Domain Value: N down
          Enumerated Domain Value Definition: North block down
          Enumerated Domain Value Definition Source: Alberta Geological Survey
        Enumerated Domain: 
          Enumerated Domain Value: S down
          Enumerated Domain Value Definition: South block down
          Enumerated Domain Value Definition Source: Alberta Geological Survey
        Enumerated Domain: 
          Enumerated Domain Value: E down
          Enumerated Domain Value Definition: East block down
          Enumerated Domain Value Definition Source: Alberta Geological Survey
        Enumerated Domain: 
          Enumerated Domain Value: W down
          Enumerated Domain Value Definition: West block down
          Enumerated Domain Value Definition Source: Alberta Geological Survey
        Enumerated Domain: 
          Enumerated Domain Value: NW down
          Enumerated Domain Value Definition: Northwest block down
          Enumerated Domain Value Definition Source: Alberta Geological Survey
        Enumerated Domain: 
          Enumerated Domain Value: NE down
          Enumerated Domain Value Definition: Northeast block down
          Enumerated Domain Value Definition Source: Alberta Geological Survey
        Enumerated Domain: 
          Enumerated Domain Value: SE down
          Enumerated Domain Value Definition: Southeast block down
          Enumerated Domain Value Definition Source: Alberta Geological Survey
        Enumerated Domain: 
          Enumerated Domain Value: SW down
          Enumerated Domain Value Definition: Southwest block down
          Enumerated Domain Value Definition Source: Alberta Geological Survey
    Attribute: 
      Attribute Label: Comment
      Attribute Definition: Comments/remarks
      Attribute Definition Source: Alberta Geological Survey
      Attribute Domain Values: 
        Unrepresentable Domain: Text
    Attribute: 
      Attribute Label: Author
      Attribute Definition: Reference author
      Attribute Definition Source: Alberta Geological Survey
      Attribute Domain Values: 
        Unrepresentable Domain: Text
    Attribute: 
      Attribute Label: Year
      Attribute Definition: Reference year
      Attribute Definition Source: Alberta Geological Survey
      Attribute Domain Values: 
        Unrepresentable Domain: Text
    Attribute: 
      Attribute Label: Title
      Attribute Definition: Reference title
      Attribute Definition Source: Alberta Geological Survey
      Attribute Domain Values: 
        Unrepresentable Domain: Text
    Attribute: 
      Attribute Label: Source
      Attribute Definition: Reference publication name and other details
      Attribute Definition Source: Alberta Geological Survey
      Attribute Domain Values: 
        Unrepresentable Domain: Text
    Attribute: 
      Attribute Label: RefPg
      Attribute Definition: Reference page number
      Attribute Definition Source: Alberta Geological Survey
      Attribute Domain Values: 
        Unrepresentable Domain: Text
    Attribute: 
      Attribute Label: PriFault
      Attribute Definition: Primary evidence of faulting (e.g.,  seismic)
      Attribute Definition Source: Alberta Geological Survey
      Attribute Domain Values: 
        Unrepresentable Domain: Text
    Attribute: 
      Attribute Label: SecFault
      Attribute Definition: Secondary evidence of faulting (e.g., thickness change)
      Attribute Definition Source: Alberta Geological Survey
      Attribute Domain Values: 
        Unrepresentable Domain: Text
    Attribute: 
      Attribute Label: ErrRange
      Attribute Definition: Estimate of the positional accuracy of the feature resulting from georeferencing, in metres
      Attribute Definition Source: Alberta Geological Survey
      Attribute Domain Values: 
        Unrepresentable Domain: Text
    Attribute: 
      Attribute Label: PubScale
      Attribute Definition: Map scale of the source publication. May be estimated.
      Attribute Definition Source: Alberta Geological Survey
      Attribute Domain Values: 
        Unrepresentable Domain: Text
Distribution Information: 
  Distributor: 
    Contact Information: 
      Contact Organization Primary: 
        Contact Organization: Alberta Geological Survey
        Contact Person: AGS Information Manager
      Contact Position: AGS Information Manager
      Contact Address: 
        Address Type: mailing and physical
        Address: Alberta Energy Regulator
        Address: 4th Floor, Twin Atria Building
        Address: 4999-98 Avenue NW
        City: Edmonton
        State or Province: Alberta
        Postal Code: T6B 2X3
        Country: Canada
      Contact Voice Telephone: (780) 638-4491
      Contact Facsimile Telephone: (780) 422-1918
      Contact Electronic Mail Address: AGS-Info@aer.ca
      Hours of Service: 8:00 a.m. to 12:00 p.m. and 1:00 p.m. to 4:30 p.m.
  Distribution Liability: The Alberta Energy Regulator/Alberta Geological Survey (AER/AGS) licenses this information under the Open Government License - Alberta. Any references to proprietary software in our documentation, and/or any use of proprietary data formats in our releases, do not constitute endorsement by the AER/AGS of any manufacturer's product.
Metadata Reference Information: 
  Metadata Date: 20151215
  Metadata Contact: 
    Contact Information: 
      Contact Organization Primary: 
        Contact Organization: Alberta Geological Survey
        Contact Person: AGS Information Manager
      Contact Position: AGS Information Manager
      Contact Address: 
        Address Type: mailing and physical
        Address: Alberta Energy Regulator
        Address: 4th Floor, Twin Atria Building
        Address: 4999-98 Avenue NW
        City: Edmonton
        State or Province: Alberta
        Postal Code: T6B 2X3
        Country: Canada
      Contact Voice Telephone: (780) 638-4491
      Contact Facsimile Telephone: (780) 422-1918
      Contact Electronic Mail Address: AGS-Info@aer.ca
      Hours of Service: 8:00 a.m. to 12:00 p.m. and 1:00 p.m. to 4:30 p.m.
  Metadata Standard Name: FGDC Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata
  Metadata Standard Version: FGDC-STD-001-1998
  Metadata Time Convention: local time
  Metadata Access Constraints: none
  Metadata Use Constraints: none
